<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "JSONiq.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="section-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <para>
    JSON and XML are both widely used for data interchange on the
    Internet. In many applications, JSON is replacing XML in Web
    Service APIs and data feeds; other applications support both
    formats. XML adds significant overhead for namespaces,
    whitespace handling, the oddities of XML Schema, and other
    things that are simply not needed in many data-oriented
    applications that require no more than simple serialization of
    program structures. On the other hand, many applications do
    need these features, and the ability to use document data
    together with traditional program data is important.
  </para>
  
  
  <para>
    JSONiq is a small and simple set of extensions to XQuery that
    add support for JSON. For applications that need only JSON, we have defined a profile called XQ--
    that removes all support for XML constructors, path expressions, user defined functions, and some other
    features considered unnecessary for most JSON queries. Syntax diagrams for XQ-- are available at
    <ulink url="http://jsoniq.org/grammars/xq--/ui.xhtml">http://jsoniq.org/grammars/xq--/ui.xhtml</ulink>.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    For applications that need to process XML together with
    JSON, we have defined a profile called XQ++ that adds these
    extensions to the full XQuery language. Syntax diagrams for
    XQ++ are available at
    <ulink url="http://jsoniq.org/grammars/xq++/ui.xhtml">http://jsoniq.org/grammars/xq++/ui.xhtml</ulink>.
  </para>
  
  
  <para>JSONiq consists of the following extensions to XQuery:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Extensions to the XQuery Data Model (XDM) to support JSON.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Support for JSON's datatypes, with a mapping to equivalent XML Schema types.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Navigation for JSON Objects and JSON Arrays.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Constructors for JSON Objects, Pairs, and JSON Arrays, using the same syntax as JSON.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Update primitives against JSON items as well as updating expressions which produce them.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>New item types, which extend sequence type matching to allow the type of JSONiq datatypes to be specified in function
      parameters, return types, and other expressions that specify XQuery types.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>JSONiq is designed to seamlessly integrate in XQuery's full composability paradigm. In particular, JSON constructors can appear in any XQuery expression, and
    any XQuery expression can appear in a JSON constructor.</para>

  <para>The namespace <code>http://jsoniq.org/functions</code> is used for functions defined by
    this specification. This namespace is exposed to the user and is bound by default to the prefix <code>jn</code>.
    For instance, the function name <code>jn:json-doc()</code> is in this namespace.</para>
  
  <para>The namespace <code>http://jsoniq.org/types</code> is used for types defined by
    this specification. This namespace is exposed to the user and is bound by default to the prefix <code>jn</code>.
    For instance, the type name <code>js:null</code> is in this namespace.</para>
  
  <para>The namespace <code>http://jsoniq.org/function-library</code> is used for library functions defined by
    this specification. This namespace is exposed to the user, however no prefix is predeclared for this namespace.
    For convenience, this document uses the prefix
    <code>libjn:</code> for names in this namespace. For instance, the function name <code>libjn:accumulate</code> is
    in this namespace.</para>
  
  <para>The namespace <code>http://jsoniq.org/errors</code> is used for the names of errors defined by this
    specification.  This namespace is exposed to the user, however no prefix is predeclared for this namespace.
    For convenience, this document uses the prefix
    <code>jerr:</code> for names in this namespace. For instance, the error name <code>jerr:JQTY0001</code> is
    in this namespace.</para>
  
  <para>The namespace <code>http://jsoniq.org/updates</code> is used for the names of update primitives defined by this
    specification. This namespace is not exposed to the user.
    For convenience, this document uses the prefix
    <code>jupd:</code> for names in this namespace. For instance, the update primitive <code>jupd:delete-from-object</code> is
    in this namespace.</para>
  
  <para>Accessors used in JSONiq Data Model use the <code>jdm:</code> prefix. These functions are not exposed to the user
    and are for explanatory purposes of the data model within this document only.
    The <code>jdm:</code> prefix is not associated with a namespace.</para>
  
</chapter>
