<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "JSound.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Schema">
  <title>Schema Documents</title>
  <section>
    <title>Scope</title>
    <para>Schema Documents have a namespace and define multiple Types in this namespace.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Schema Document properties</title>
    <para>Schema Documents are (serialized) JSON objects which have the following properties</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>$namespace (JSON string): the namespace (URI) in which the types defined in this Schema Document live.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$about (JSON value): free content (documentation, comments, ...).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$imports (JSON array of objects) : used to import Types located in other Schema Documents (i.e., in other Namespaces).
        Imports are not recursive, i.e., importing a Schema Document does not import the further Schema Documents that it may itself import.</para>
        <para>Each JSON object in this JSON array has the following properties:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>$namespace (JSON string): the namespace in which the Types being imported live.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>$location (JSON string): a hint about where to find the Schema Document for this namespace.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>$prefix (JSON string): the prefix used in Qualified Names to refer to Types in the above namespace. Must not contain a colon.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$types (JSON array of objects representing Types) : the Types defined in this document. How these objects look like is explained in subsequent sections.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>This Schema Document defines two Atomic Types in the "http://www.example.com/my-schema" namespace and with the local names "small-number" and "big-number".</para>
    <programlisting>
{
  "$namespace" : "http://www.example.com/my-schema",
  "$types" : [
    {
      "$kind" : "atomic",
      "$name" : "small-number",
      "$baseType" : "integer",
      "$enumeration" : [ 1, 2, 4, 8 ]
    },
    {
      "$kind" : "atomic",
      "$name" : "Q{http://www.example.com/my-schema}big-number",
      "$baseType" : "integer",
      "$enumeration" : [ 1000, 2000, 4000, 8000 ]
    }
  ]
}
    </programlisting>
    <para>This Schema Document defines one Object Type in the "http://www.example.com/my-new-schema" namespace named "small-and-big".</para>
    <programlisting>
{
  "$namespace" : "http://www.example.com/my-new-schema",
  "$imports" : [
    {
      "$namespace" : "http://www.example.com/my-schema",
      "$prefix" : "other"
    }
  ],
  "$types" : [
    {
      "$kind" : "object",
      "$name" : "small-and-big",
      "$content" : {
        "small" : { "$type" : "other:small-number" },
        "big" : { "$type" : "other:big-number", "$optional" : true }
      }
    }
  ]
}
    </programlisting>
    <para>Given this set of two Schema Documents, the following JSON object:</para>
    <programlisting>
{
  "small" : 4
}
    </programlisting>
    <para>is valid against the Type named "Q{http://www.example.com/my-new-schema}small-and-big".</para>
    <para>This JSON object is not valid, because the value associated with "big" is not in the value space of the
    Type "Q{http://www.example.com/my-schema}big-number".</para>
    <programlisting>
{
  "small" : 4,
  "big" : 3
}
    </programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Type Names and references to Types</title>
    <para>Type Names are Qualified Names, made of a namespace and of a local name, as described in the former chapter.</para>
    <para>Types names are used to (optionally) name Types, or to refer to another Type as a base type.</para>
    <para>
      References to Types that are defined in the same Schema Document can be referred to with no prefix as well: the namespace is that of the defining Schema Document.
      If there is a collision with Builtin Type names, the locally defined Type has precedence (the Builtin Type is hidden).
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Types</title>
    <para>
      There are four kinds of Types: atomic, object, array and union.
    </para>
    <para>
      Types are either Builtin, in which case their name is in no namespace, or Derived.
    </para>
    <para>The topmost Type is builtin and is named "item".</para>
    <para>The topmost Object Type is builtin and is named "object".</para>
    <para>The topmost Array Type is builtin and is named "array".</para>
    <para>The topmost Atomic Type is builtin and is named "atomic". There are many further Builtin Atomic Types.</para>
    <para>
      Derived Types are always defined by restricting the value space of a
      <emphasis>base type</emphasis> by means of <emphasis>facets</emphasis>. They have a JSON object representation.
    </para>
    <para>
      Derived Object Types are always directly derived from "object".
      Derived Array Types are always directly derived from "array".
      Derived Union Types are always directly derived from "item".
      Derived Atomic Types may be derived from any other Atomic Type.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Derived Type properties</title>
    <para>A Derived Type has the following properties:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>$kind (JSON string): the kind of the Type. One of "atomic, "object", "array", "union".</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$name (JSON string): a string containing the Qualified Name (as defined above) of this Type.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$baseType (JSON string): a string containing the Qualified Name of the Type which is the base type of this Type.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$about (JSON value): free content (documentation, comments, ...).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>various facets properties. Which facets are available defines on the $kind of the Type.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>There are the following constraints on these properties:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>$name is optional and must live in the namespace of the Schema Document in which this Type is defined.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A prefix may not appear twice in the $imports.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Types defined directly in the top-level $types array must be named.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$baseType must refer to a known Type - builtin, in the same Schema Document or in an imported Schema Document. In particular,
        if a prefix is used, it must be bound to an imported namespace.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If $kind is "object", $baseType must be "object" if provided.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If $kind is "array", $baseType must be "array" if provided.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If $kind is "union", $baseType must be "item" if provided.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If $kind is "atomic", $baseType must be the Qualified Name of an existing Atomic Type.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Here is an example of an invalid Schema Document, because it does not fulfill many of the above constraints.</para>
    <programlisting>
{
  "$namespace" : "http://www.example.com/my-schema",
  "$types" : [
    {
      "$kind" : "atomic",
      "$name" : "type1",
      "$baseType" : "unbound:type", (: prefix is not bound :)
      "$maxInclusive" : 4
    },
    {
      "$kind" : "atomic",
      "$name" : "Q{http://www.example.com/other}type2", (: the namespace must match that of the Schema document :)
      "$baseType" : "integer",
      "$maxInclusive" : 4
    },
    {
      "$kind" : "atomic",
      "$name" : "Q{http://www.example.com/my-schema}type3",
      "$baseType" : "object", (: base type MUST also be an atomic type :)
      "$maxInclusive" : 4
    },
    {
      "$kind" : "object",
      "$name" : "object1",
      "$baseType" : "type1" (: base type MUST be "object":)
      "$content" : {}
    },
    {
      "$kind" : "object",
      "$name" : "object2",
      "$baseType" : "object1" (: base type MUST be "object":)
    }
  ]
}
    </programlisting>
    <para>There are two facets common to all types:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>$enumeration (array of JSON values): Constrains a value space to a specified set of values.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>$constraints (array of JSON strings): Constrains a value space to the values for which a set of JSONiq queries evaluates to true. In these JSONiq queries, the context item is bound to the Serialized Instance being validated, after parsing.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <programlisting>
{
  "$namespace" : "http://www.example.com/my-schema",
  "$types" : [
    {
      "$kind" : "object"
      (: "$baseType" : "object" is implicit :)
      "$name" : "two-objects",
      "$enumeration" : [ { "foo" : "bar" }, {} ] (: only these two objects :)
    },
    {
      "$kind" : "array"
      (: "$baseType" : "array" is implicit :)
      "$name" : "uniform-array",
      "$constraints" : [ "every $i in 1 to size($$) satisfies deep-equals($$($i), $$(1))" ]  (: all members must be the same :)
    },
  ]
}
    </programlisting>
    <para>The following JSON object is valid against Q{http://www.example.com/my-schema}two-objects.</para>
    <programlisting>
{ "foo" : "bar" }
    </programlisting>
    <para>The following JSON array is valid against Q{http://www.example.com/my-schema}uniform-array.</para>
    <programlisting>
[ 42, 42, 42 ]
    </programlisting>
  </section>
</chapter>
